[SOUND EFFECTS]
PHILIP GREENSPUN: All right.
Let's talk about aircraft
ownership and maintenance.
Some of this stuff actually,
oddly enough, is on the test.
What does it cost
to own an airplane?
Most people say, I
can't afford that.
But then you see them
buy a brand new car
or renovate their
kitchen for $200,000.
So I don't know what
their excuse is.
It's actually not expensive
to own a four-seat airplane.
There's so many out there.
There were more pilots
in the '70s and '80s,
when these airplanes were
built in large quantities.
The owner of East
Coast Aero Club, Mark,
he says that, in the '80s,
there was a waiting list even
for a tie down at Hanscom.
Now there's ample parking.
The hangar space is
still a little bit tight,
but if you just want to
get a Cessna and pay,
it's actually a lot cheaper to
tie a Cessna down at Hanscom
than it is to park
a car in Cambridge.
And there's plenty of room.
He said every
firefighter, every teacher
used to have a family airplane.
So the airplanes are
relatively inexpensive to buy--
$20,000, $30,000 for something
that's airworthy for VFR use,
for basic VFR use.
And you can see the prices here.
The depreciation would
be pretty close to zero
for those lower-end airplanes.
Anyway, all that said,
it's still cheaper
to rent from a flight
school if you're
going to fly 100 hours a year,
paying $150 or $200 an hour
to a flight school is still
cheaper, and it's a lot easier.
For people for whom
owning may actually
make a little bit
of rational sense,
it never truly
makes sense compared
to just getting everywhere
in your Toyota Camry.
That if you fly a whole ton,
more than 100 hours a year,
and the fixed costs of
insurance and storage and stuff
won't kill you, if you
have to use the airplane
to make regular long trips
somewhere and then just park it
away from the home airport,
then it makes sense.
And a lot of people,
also, you know
you can't fly, if you
have multiple airplanes,
you can't fly them
all at the same time.
And even one airplane,
it's a little bit hard
to use everyday the way
you would use a car.
So partnerships with two to
four people are pretty common.
And that cuts the
cost dramatically
without really
impairing the utility.
I shared an airplane
for years with a guy,
and I don't think we
ever conflicted on when
we wanted to use the plane.
All right.
This is some stuff that you
want to know a little bit.
If you're an owner,
it's really critical.
And if you're a renter, some
of the stuff is still relevant.
So the owner or operator, if
you think about a leaseback
airplane to the flight
school, the leaseback owner
is any individual, perhaps.
And the flight school
becomes the operator.
And they're the ones
who are primarily
responsible for making sure
the airplane is airworthy,
that it gets its
annual inspection,
and that it has a logbook.
However, the pilot
is also responsible.
And if the pilot knows that
something's inoperative,
and it's not required,
then it's still
legal to fly the airplane
in a lot of circumstances
as long as that piece of
equipment is placarded inop.
And maybe the breaker
is pulled, for example,
on a GPS unit
that's not working.
After maintenance,
then a private pilot
with no passengers
can make entry
in the logbook saying that
the test flight was done.
The core inspection
is every 12 months.
For a privately
owned airplane, it
has to have an
annual inspection.
Typically it won't
fly a whole lot
more than 100 hours during that
year if it's just one person
flying it.
But the 100-hour
requirement only
becomes necessary
when the airplane
is operated commercially,
like at a flight school.
So that's 100 hours of flight
time, not engine running time.
So if it's taxiing
around the airport,
the engine might be running
for 120 or 130 hours
to build up 100
hours of flight time.
You say, well,
god, these airlines
must have to tear
the airplane apart,
open all the inspection
panels every week or two.
Jets have their own
maintenance schedule that
supersedes this FAA guidance.
Even modest-sized
jets often have a 300
or a 600-hour service Interval.
The Pilatus PC-12, it was
recently extended to 300 hours,
for example.
OK, Tina covered this before.
The transponder has to
be inspected and sort of
recertified every
couple of years.
Emergency locator transmitters--
if it's a civil airplane,
91.207 says it
has to have an ELT
except in certain circumstances.
So gliders, helicopters, things
like that don't really need it,
I don't think.
Maybe the glider does.
I don't think so.
So the FAA really
wants to ensure
that every aircraft that's
flying around in the US
has a comprehensive
logbook going back
to the birth of the aircraft,
the birth of the propeller,
and the birth of the engine.
Engines, when they get
remanufactured by somebody
like Lycoming or Continental,
they get a zero-time logbook.
So that logbook might only
go back four or five years.
But the logbook for the
airframe should go back
to when it was made.
If the logbook ever
gets lost, the airplane
is significantly
devalued, because stuff
has to be reconstructed.
And you can never really be
sure what's happened to it.
OK.
There are airworthiness
directives that legally
have to be applied to aircraft.
If the manufacturer
issues a service bulletin,
you don't have to do that,
especially if you're not
operating the
airplane commercially,
like as an airline or a charter.
But airworthiness
directives are mandatory.
So let's see if I can
think of an example.
I think there were some Cessna
seats that were sliding back,
so people were trying
to fly their Cessna
and the seat wasn't really
locked into position.
So that's the kind of thing
where an airworthiness
directive would be negotiated
between Cessna and the FAA.
And it would be issued, and they
might say, within the next 10
flight hours, you have to
go and get new seat rails
for your Cessna to make sure
that it doesn't slide back
inadvertently.
If there's a plane--
if there's something
really serious,
they may issue an emergency
airworthiness directive
and say, everything's
grounded until you
apply this fix or change.
Here is just an
example, actually.
What did we find here?
This was for Cirruses.
Ah.
In-flight cabin
door separation--
that's not good.
[LAUGHS] One was
total separation.
One was retained
by the door strut.
We're issuing this AD to prevent
in-flight failure of the cabin
door.
OK, well, it's nice to
have two doors, I guess.
That's the takeaway
from this one.
I don't know what they said that
you have to do-- yeah, threads,
leaves, blah, blah, blah.
Oh, but it says within 50 hours.
See that?
Within the next 50
hours time in service.
So they don't consider
that an emergency.
And actually, if you
ever do take off,
don't slam an aircraft door.
They tend to be fragile.
The latches, various techniques
have been tried over the years
by various manufacturers.
None of them are as
foolproof as car doors,
because they don't have the
weight budget that a car has.
So if a door does
pop open in flight,
it's actually not
hazardous as long
as you're not so
startled that you
do something crazy on takeoff.
They'll usually pop open
just as you're climbing out,
and you're like, whoa,
what's that noise?
Anyway, just remember, as Tina
said, keep flying the airplane.
And don't over-focus
on something
that's not related to the
aircraft attitude and power.
OK, part 43 is mostly stuff
that certified AMT mechanics
need to know.
It's illegal, actually for--
this is one reason
why owning an airplane
is better than owning a boat.
It's illegal for you to
work on your own airplane,
more or less.
[LAUGHS] So you have to have an
FAA-certified mechanic do it.
You can't spend every weekend
monkeying with your airplane.
There are a handful of things
pilots are allowed to do.
You can replace a tire.
You can add oil.
You can-- there's an
enumerated list, 31 items.
A lot of those
are kind of more--
you can change a spark plug--
related to bush pilots.
If you're up in Alaska, or
northern Minnesota, or out
in the middle of Maine, and
you want to change something,
instead of being stuck, you can
carry a spark plug and a wrench
and get yourself
back to the hangar.
But it's unconventional for
people with certified airplanes
to do much in the
way of maintenance.
One exception is
owner-assisted annuals.
Some people who are very
mechanically inclined
like to work with
an AMT and help out.
If you do this stuff,
you have to sign it off
by making a logbook entry
with your certificate number
and what kind of certificate.
So if you change
the oil, you still
have to log it even though
you're not a mechanic.
You just say, I'm a pilot, and
here's my pilot certificate
number.
All right, if that's
too much work,
and you still really just want
to own an airplane because you
want to say that
I own an airplane,
you can buy an airplane.
And then if you're not going
to fly it 200 hours a year
or more, you can lease
it to a flight school
and let the flight
school be responsible
for the maintenance.
A lot of people do this to
take advantage of depreciation.
Let's say they're
a medical doctor.
They start a side business
working with a flight school,
and they're now in the
aircraft rental business.
And they take a 100%
deduction for their airplane.
It hasn't really been
completely tested by the IRS.
Leasing is supposed
to be a passive loss,
and you're not
supposed to offset it
against active income.
So people come up with various
gimmicks where the flight
school is marketing
their aircraft for rental
to other people.
Anyway, they're taking
$700,000 or $800,000 write-off
in one year against their
million dollar income
as a physician.
And now they have
a free airplane.
And that's why you can
go to the flight school
and rent one of these beautiful
new airplanes for $250 an hour.
It sounds like a lot,
but take advantage of it,
because they're basically giving
you the airplane for free.
OK, what if that's
not enough work?
Well, go to Oshkosh in July.
I'll be there.
And we can go check out
all the kit airplanes,
and you can meet
people who say they've
spent 13 years building
their airplane,
and now they're
finally flying it.
So in theory, the airplane
has to be built by this--
the intent was some
person who was then
going to fly it had
to build half of it.
But you know, LLCs
are also people,
as far as the regulations
are concerned.
So basically, the LLC becomes
the builder of record.
And the LLC is formed between
somebody who actually knows
what he or she is
doing and the pilot who
just wants to fly the cool
experimental airplane.
And then when the
builder's finished,
the pilot buys out the builder.
There are a lot of
limitations on experimentals.
Oh yeah, another technique
is the factory-assist build.
So to show that people
have done a lot of work,
they'll go down to the
factory, and they'll change
their clothing every two hours.
And they'll have all these
pictures of themselves doing
various work on the aircraft.
And then they can
show that to the FAA
and say, look, I was
putting on the wings.
I was doing this.
I was doing that.
[LAUGHS]
All right, you can't use
the aircraft commercially.
And if your passenger
gets into the airplane,
right in front of
the passenger will
be this scary-looking sign that
says, this is experimental,
doesn't meet FAA standards.
So the passenger is warned
that there's a lot more risk
than flying a Cessna.
So you might say,
well, why is it riskier
than a Cessna or a Cirrus?
And I talked to Alan
Klapmeier about this,
one of the founders of Cirrus.
I said, how come these
experimentals have
so much better numbers
for payload or speed
than certified planes
like the Cirrus?
So part of it is
that they're relieved
of a lot of the
forgivingness requirements
of certified airplanes.
So they're a little
bit trickier to handle.
You might have a
higher stall speed.
They're just not as
idiot-proof and as stable
as a Cessna Piper or Cirrus.
The other issue is
that they don't have
as much redundant structure.
With an experimental,
you're allowed
to assume that the construction
process was perfect,
that there were no defects,
there were no missing screws,
that nobody dropped a tool and
damaged part of the structure
during construction.
But a certified airplane,
you have to show to the FAA
that even if all
kinds of bad stuff
goes on during manufacturing,
and then the airplane's
buttoned up so that
those parts can't really
be inspected
afterwards, it still
meets all of the
structural requirements.
That's why you see
these crazy YouTube
videos of wings being tested.
The transport category
aircraft are only
supposed to be
certified to 2.5 Gs,
and the wings don't break
until they put 9 Gs on them.
Partly they're over-designing
because it's good engineering
practice, but also
because they have
to over-design to
some extent because it
has to do 2.5 G's even
if a lot of mistakes
were made during
the manufacturing.
So experimentals-- there's
not really a free lunch.
It's not like they're better
than a Cessna or Piper.
They're subject to kind
of different rules.
The one element where
they are arguably better
is that, with composites,
you're allowed to--
it becomes practical to
make arbitrary shapes.
If you're fabricating
sheet metal,
there's a limit
to how exotic you
can get at a reasonable price,
whereas planes like the Cirrus
and then some of these
experimentalists,
you can have a nice
smooth skin, and you
can make any shape you want.
It's closer to an ideal airflow.
But otherwise,
there's no free lunch.
If it has better payload,
that's because they took out
all the redundant structure
that makes a certified airplane
a little safer.
All right, renter pilots
are still responsible,
to some extent, for this stuff.
You've got to make sure
the aircraft is airworthy.
You can't pin it all
on the flight school.
If you see something hanging
loose, or there's no oil in it,
then it's your responsibility
to call the mechanic over
to re-secure the panel
or put some oil in.
You want to make sure
that the airplane has
airworthiness certificate.
The registration
used to last forever.
Now it expires
every three years.
So I guess if you're in a
brand new flight school,
and you don't know
everybody there,
it's worth at least paying some
attention to the registration.
The AFM/POH, or owner's
manual, if you want
to be colloquial about it--
that has to be
onboard the aircraft.
Usually the weight and balance
is not a separate thing.
It's just inside the POH.
And you have to also
report accidents.
We'll talk about that more in
the seaplane lecture, [LAUGHS]
since sloppiness in
the seaplane tends
to be more likely to
lead to an accident.
All right, so you are
responsible for the operation
of the aircraft.
And with responsibility comes
the authority and ability
to deviate from the
rules in an emergency.
You can just say,
you know, Cirrus
707 whiskey tango emergency
landing at this nearby Air
Force base.
And they can't really
bust you for that.
If later they come
and say, well, we
want to know why you landed
at the Air Force base,
then you have to you
respond with what
led you to want to do that.
But if they don't request you to
do that, then there's no need.
So basically, you can
just read the slide.
But abort the mission
if you see something
broken during the pre-flight.
All right, here's a standard
airworthiness certificate
there on the bottom right.
When was it issued?
1995.
So I think that's when
the airplane was built.
The airworthiness
certificate should tell you
when the manufacturing
process terminated.
Start shopping.
So if you look at
Controller.com,
that's where your
higher-end aircraft are.
And Trade-a-Plane is
that big yellow book
that some of you guys may
have seen at flight schools.
Barnstormers.com is
the homebuilt center.
Before we take
questions, I'll just
close by telling
you all that's fine.
But it's not really rational.
Having done one aileron roll
and one loop in my life,
do I need a GameBird?
No.
But it's only $400 grand,
and I want a GameBird.
[LAUGHS] And wouldn't it be
cool to arrive in a GameBird?
Look at that luggage space.
You could put in probably three
packs of crush-proof cigarettes
[LAUGHS] and a
spare pair of socks,
like Charles Lindbergh
used to travel with.
So anyway, yeah that
ownership stuff--
it's never a rational
decision to buy an aircraft
unless you're planning
on dying rich.
Why not?
Actually jetAVIVA
has this thing.
Their whole tagline for
this airplane brokerage
is life is short, fly a jet.
[LAUGHS]
Does anyone have any exciting
questions about maintenance
and your responsibilities
as a pilot?
OK, there's a little
bit of interaction
there between the
pilot and the mechanic.
You can't practically
check everything.
You have to rely
on mechanics, who
are generally quite reliable.
And they're FAA-certificated.
But you have to
have a little bit
of common sense about not
accepting a broken airplane
or helicopter.
Oh, [INAUDIBLE]
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
build your own airplane
how [INAUDIBLE] does the process
of [INAUDIBLE] certification
[INAUDIBLE]
PHILIP GREENSPUN: If you
build your own airplane?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: My friend
Christian can answer that.
There may be a YouTube video.
But anyway, I think
the FAA is supposed
to inspect at one or two
points during the construction.
I'm not 100% sure
about that, But I
think that they may come in.
More importantly,
there is, like,
40 hours of flight testing
that has to be done.
And you can't go
over populated areas
during that flight testing.
And you get cut loose, I
think, after 40 or 50 hours
in the experimental world.
It's never been
attractive to me.
I mean, if you talk to the
people who do experimentals,
they're really passionate
about building and tinkering.
They actually have very
few hours of flight time
accumulated.
And that becomes a problem,
because their pilot--
even if they were a good
pilot when they started,
after spending 13 years
in a garage building,
their pilot skills
are pretty rusty.
[LAUGHS]
TINA SRIVASTAVA: I
would also recommend
that you ask Sebastian.
If you guys remember, Sebastian
came yesterday afternoon
from the flying club.
And he was discussing
how they're
getting that plane refurbished.
He had a picture with
the wing not attached,
and now the wing is attached.
So I believe that he's going
through that airworthiness
process right now.
So definitely recommend
you talk to Sebastian.
And then the other
thing I would just
add to aircraft
ownership in general
is that there are also a lot of
opportunities where there are--
basically, you can become
part of a group that
partially owns an airplane.
So there's a bunch
of clubs around here
where, for example, there
are three planes that
are owned by 60 people.
And so you kind of
timeshare those planes.
And a number of the other
instructors of this course
have done that.
So you might have heard Luke
or Marissa talk about that.
And so they have some
planes, for example,
in Beverly, where
there are three planes,
and a bunch of people own it.
And so you can
timeshare the plane,
and they have to be very
mindful about these types
of maintenance aspects, as well.
So it's kind of an in-between
cost of renting versus owning
your own airplane by yourself.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yeah,
and if you want to--
the Experimental
Aircraft Association,
which runs Oshkosh, they
have chapter meetings
all over the country
all the time.
They're kind of the most social
folks in the aviation world.
So if you want to find out what
it's like to build your own kit
airplane or design your
own airplane from scratch,
those people will
be happy to hang out
with you, at least every
month, all over the country--
EAA.